原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/nl0QDkAwxWY
原视频发布日期：20201013
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
Over the years I've talked about a lot of rockets.
这些年来 我谈了很多火箭
I mean while the US only has a handful of operational launch vehicle
我是指 虽然美国现在只有一小部分运载火箭在服役
there has been hundreds of different designs over the decades and around the globe.
但是全世界几十年来 有数百种不同的运载火箭设计
Not all rockets were successful.
并非所有的火箭都是成功的
Many made it to orbit.
许多火箭都进入了轨道
And some of them were among the ugliest pieces of engineering to ever come out of a discipline
其中一些火箭有着最丑陋的工程设计
where sleek designs are supposed to be required for aerodynamic reasons.
而这样丑陋的设计其实与空气动力学相违背
I mean there's limits as to what you can reasonably do with rocket designs due to the laws of physics
我是指 由于物理定律 合理的火箭设计是有限的
and rocket design is usually a team effort
而且火箭设计通常由一个团队完成
which means if you want to churn out an ugly launch vehicle
这意味着如果你想制造出一个丑陋的运载火箭
you have to actually assemble an entire team of aesthetically challenged engineers
那么你就得组建一整个的反美学的工程师团队
and have them fight against the natural tendency for rockets to look cool.
并让他们对抗火箭那看起来天生就很酷的气质
So anyway as a break from digging into the math or physics or history or engineering
所以不管怎么说 暂时不细究数学 物理 历史或工程
I just wanted to highlight some of the greatest sins in the field of rocket design.
现在我只想着重讨论下火箭设计领域的一些最大的罪状
If you are a student of aerospace engineering
如果你是航空航天工程专业的学生
then consider these next few minutes to be some examples of things not to do.
那么接下来的这几分钟就当是一些别去做的反面例子吧
虽然Able曾经是美军音标字母标准 en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allied_military_phonetic_spelling_alphabets
但是Able本身是一个火箭分级名称所以还是翻译成其本意 能 en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Able_(rocket_stage)
So in no particular order let's start with the Atlas-Able.
所以 不按照特定的顺序 让我们从能当宇宙神宇宙神-能火箭开始
I'm sorry but this looks like a massive mutant bowling pin or something.
实在抱歉 但这看起来就像一个巨大的变异保龄球瓶之类的东西
This was early on in the life of the Atlas
实际上这是早期的宇宙神火箭
when they were trying to adapt it into a launch vehicle.
当他们试图将其改造成运载火箭时
And while the Atlas could reach orbit on its own
虽然宇宙神可以单级入轨
they wanted to then send a spacecraft past the moon.
但是他们想让航天器飞掠月球
So the engineers took the second and third stages from the Vanguards
所以工程师们从先锋号火箭上取下了第二级和第三级
and put them on top of the much more powerful Atlas booster.
并把他们放在更强大的宇宙神助推器之上
So yeah there's a whole joke in here by the way about you know
那么没错 顺便说个纯粹的笑话
how helicopters fly because they're so ugly the ground repels them.
直升机之所以能飞 是因为它们太丑陋了 地面会排斥它们
Clearly this doesn't apply to rockets
显然 这不适用于火箭
because for the Atlas-Able, two of them never made it off the ground because of static failures
因为对于宇宙神-能火箭来说 其中有两枚发生了静态点火故障而从未离开地面
and three failed in flight.
而另外三枚在发射过程中失败
And that was a hundred percent perfect unsuccessful launch record.
而这就是百分百完美的失败发射记录
Granted there was the similar Thor-Able design
虽说有类似的雷神-能火箭的设计
which you know you did the same idea but used a Thor.
不过是一级火箭换成了雷神
The Thor booster is a little skinnier so it looks a lot less ridiculous
但因为雷神助推器比较瘦 所以看起来不那么滑稽
and yes it does have the benefit of being successful.
是的 相比之下它确实成功过 这是好的
Let's be clear though.
不过我们要明确一点
A rocket could be highly successful and still staggeringly ugly at the same time
一枚火箭可以在丑得惊人的同时非常成功
such as the Ariane 4.
如阿丽亚娜4
Now the first four iterations of Ariane were never elegant.
那么 阿丽亚娜的前四次迭代完全不优雅
The size difference between the stages, the fairing shape
各级之间的尺寸差异 整流罩的形状
the conical extensions covering the engines that help the aerodynamics
覆盖在发动机上的锥形延伸部分 虽然有助于空气动力学的发展
but to the detriment of the looks.
但却损害了外观
The Ariane 4 specifically had the option to use two different types of strap-on boosters on the first stage.
特别是阿丽亚娜4 其芯一级可以选择使用两种不同类型的捆绑助推器
And in the case of the AR 44LP had a pair of fat liquid boosters
而在AR 44LP的构型情况下 有一对比较胖的液体助推器
and two skinny solid boosters to create something that is aesthetically jarring on many levels.
以及另外两个瘦小的固体助推器 这导致了其在多种层面上都很丑陋
But this configuration launched many times.
但这种配置发射了很多次
25 successful launches.
进行了25次的成功的发射
The other highly successful rocket which never looked elegant to me was the Proton.
另一个在我看来完全不优雅的高度成功的火箭是质子号
For me it's like Soviet architecture in rocket form.
对我来说 它就像火箭形式的苏联架构
And I know a lot of people like it and it has launched many historic payloads
而且我知道很多人喜欢它 它也发射了很多载入史册的有效载荷
but I've never gone over the disappointment of realizing that first stage isn't surrounded by strap-on boosters.
但我从来没有完全地摆脱这种失望感 那就是芯一级其实并没有被捆绑助推器所包围
That design is all bolted together on the ground
在质子号的设计中 在地面上的时候 周围的储罐是使用螺栓固定死的
and they use that because the seven tanks have to fit on you know rail transport.
而之所这样设计 是因为火车得能装下这样的7个储罐的尺寸
And they couldn't do anything bigger.
所以不能做得更大了
Apparently at one point during testing they actually filled this whole thing with vodka
很显然 某次测试过程中 他们居然把这整个火箭装满了伏特加
so maybe that explains why the engineers were happy to overlook the aesthetic shortcomings of it.
所以也许这就解释了为什么工程师们乐于忽略它的美学缺点
Here's the thing though the Proton was known as the UR-500, universal rocket
可问题是质子号被称为UR-500型通用火箭
and it was actually pretty tame compared to the UR-700 or the UR-900
而与UR-700或UR-900相比 UR-500就不值一提了
which just kept on bolting tanks together at random
这是因为UR-700和UR-900只是一直用螺栓将储罐随机地连接在一起
until they had something that was supposed to go to the moon or even mars.
直到把规模堆积到能把足够多的有效载荷运送到月球甚至火星
So consider that had the US not won the moon race in 1969.
因此 考虑到如果美国没有赢得1969年的登月竞赛
One of these monstrosities might have been built if the N1 kept failing.
与此同时如果N1一直失败 可能就会制造出这样的一种UR怪兽
There's some alternate history out there
有一些未曾设想的道路
where people are praising the Proton and the UR-700 as the rocket that brought us to the moon.
在那样的历史中 质子号和UR-700因为成为了登月火箭而被人们称赞
豁
Okay number four is OTRAG system
好吧 第四个是OTRAG系统
which was supposed to be made of clusters of pipe like thrust elements.
这应该是由一簇像管子一样的推力元件组成
This was an interesting idea to bring rocket cost down
这个有趣的想法 可以降低火箭的成本
by standardizing all the parts and clustering them together.
因为这样可以将标准化所有的部件 并将它们集中在一起
Unfortunately to scale the idea up, the result looked like a bundle of drinking straws
不幸的是 为了扩大这个想法的规模 结果就看起来像一捆饮料吸管
or in one case, a giant silver office block.
或者在另一种情况下变成一个巨大的银色办公大楼
I mean the goal was to make it cheap but not make it look good.
我是指 这样的设计目标是让它便宜而不是变得好看
OTRAG was of course somewhat notorious for projects links to african dictators
当然 OTRAG因与非洲寡头的项目联系而臭名昭著
and of course the top-tier dictators like to get their hands on ballistic missiles
当然 顶级寡头们确实也喜欢整弹道导弹
but what if you took a bunch of Scud missiles and bundled them together to make a multi-stage rocket.
或者比如说 把一堆飞毛腿导弹捆绑在一起 做一个多级火箭
That's what was tried by Iraq in the late 1980s.
这就是伊拉克在80年代末所做的尝试
They've actually started a civilian satellite program and were trying to get it flown on an Ariane 4
他们实际上已经开始了一个民用卫星计划 并试图用阿丽亚娜4号火箭进行发射
but deteriorating international relations meant that it was impossible.
但不断恶化的国际关系意味着这是不可能的
So instead they began to develop their own launch vehicles based on the Scud missile.
所以他们反而开始在飞毛腿导弹的基础上研发自己的运载火箭
Unfortunately the only images I have of this
遗憾的是 我所掌握的这枚火箭的唯一图片
are terrible from your grainy videotapes and old UN reports.
来自于很糟糕的画质粗糙的录像带和旧的联合国报告
But the drawings I have show a classic example of what happens in Kerbal Space Program
但是 这个结构图说明了一个经典的坎巴拉太空计划中会发生的例子
when you've only unlocked the small fuel tanks and engines but you need a big launch vehicle.
也就是在只解锁了小燃料储罐和发动机组件的情况下要制造大火箭的时候
It was built around six modified Scud missiles.
它由六枚改装过的飞毛腿导弹制造而成
Five in the first stage. One in the second stage.
五枚在一级 一枚在二级
And then a third stage which was probably also adapted from another missile.
而三级也可能是由另一枚导弹改装而成的
There was only one test flight of this and it had a dummy second and third stage
这枚火箭只进行了一次携带二三级模型的试飞
but it looks like it failed after 45 seconds.
但看起来在发射后45秒就失败了
Possibly because the stage separation system fired early or it lost the will to live.
可能是因为分级系统的提前启动 或者是它失去了生存的意愿
They did actually demonstrate that they could make this monstrosity fly
他们确实验证了这枚怪兽的飞行能力
but before they progressed to another flight, there was that whole Gulf War thing.
但在他们进行另一次发射之前 发生了海湾战争
And afterwards Iraq was forced to give up its long-range missiles to stop them doing bad things with them.
之后 为了阻止用导弹做坏事 伊拉克被迫放弃其远程导弹
At the time we thought that meant threatening their neighbors
那时其他国家认为这会威胁伊拉克的邻国
but it might equally have been to stymie their engineers who thought that add-and-abide was a good idea.
但这同样可能是为了阻止那些认为不停捆绑是好设计的工程师们
Clustering together small rockets to make a bigger rocket has also seen in the US.
在美国也曾出现过 把小火箭集中在一起做大火箭的做法
In the form of the Conestoga 1620
这就是Conestoga 1620
which looks like a bunch of white crayons held together with black rubber bands.
看起来就像一堆白色蜡笔用黑色橡皮筋固定在了一起
I guess the rocket builders were planning on getting a bulk discount on Castor 4 solid rocket motors
我猜火箭制造者们正打算以批发价格购买Castor 4固体火箭发动机
because they used seven in the rocket.
因为他们在这枚种火箭中使用了7个这样的发动机
They would ignite four then two and then one as it ascended.
在火箭上升的时候 会先启动4台发动机 接着是2个 然后是1个
They actually had a number of different designs based on the same idea
实际上 基于同样的想法 他们还有很多别的不同的设计
but this was the only one that ever flew.
但这是其中唯一一个飞过的火箭
To its credit while the rocket looked squat and ugly on the launch pad
值得称道的是 虽然火箭在发射台上看起来又矮又丑
when it finally flew failed and was aborted
但当它飞行失败并中止的时候
it did produce some very pretty patterns in the sky
它确实在天空中产生了一些非常漂亮的花纹
as the still burning boosters went their separate ways.
因为还在点火的助推器各奔东西
The polar opposite of this is a rocket with a single big solid rocket booster.
与此截然相反的是一种只有一个大的固体火箭助推器的火箭
That is the Ares X-I which has a big solid rocket booster from a Space Shuttle with a boilerplate on top
那就是战神X-1(口胡，应该是战神1-X) 其使用了航天飞机的固体助推器 并在其上加了一个模型
that was supposed to represent the planned hydrolox upper stages and the Orion capsule.
而真正的战神1火箭的上面搭载的应该是氢氧上面级和猎户座飞船
So this has the effect of making it resemble a snake
那么 这使它长得像一只蛇
that has consumed a substantial meal and is now going to spend the next week digesting it.
像那种刚吃完一顿丰盛的饭菜 而要用下一周的时间来进行消化的蛇
It looks upside down with a fatter stage on the front.
它看起来像是倒过来了 前面的分级更大
A lot of this is because of the equally ugly politics
这很大程度上是因为同样丑陋的政治
that tried to push this as a cargo vehicle for the ISS
试图强行将这枚火箭作为国际空间站的货运飞船来使用
instead of the commercial vehicles which would take flight a year later
而不是一年后进行发射的商业火箭
So far it's the only Shuttle-derived launch vehicle to actually fly
到目前为止 它是唯一一个飞起来的航天飞机的衍生运载火箭
even if it was cancelled before it could launch again.
即使它还没来得及再次发射就被取消了
There are a lot of different Shuttle derived launch vehicle concepts which never made it off paper
有很多不同的航天飞机的衍生运载火箭概念 但从来没有离开过纸面
which means technically they don't qualify for this
这意味着从技术上讲 这些火箭并不符合今天视频的主题
but I'm including a couple
但我会介绍一部分
because technically part of them did actually fly as boosters on the Space Shuttle.
因为从另一种技术角度上讲 它们中的一部分确实是作为助推器在航天飞机上飞行的
And you know there are eyesores that leap off the pages of these white papers.
而且你懂的 有些碍眼的东西会从这些白皮书的纸面上跳出来
The SRB-X has been described as the single worst Shuttle derived launcher ever proposed.
SRB-X被形容为有史以来最糟糕的航天飞机的衍生运载火箭
It was a proposal for a geostationary orbit capable booster for the Air Force.
这是为空军提出的地球静止轨道运载火箭的方案
And it probably started out as a sensible idea to build a rocket using the Shuttle boosters
而很可能这一开始确实是一个明智的想法 也就是利用航天飞机助推器制造火箭
to boost another core with a Shuttle booster on it and then extra upper stages.
并助推另一个带有航天飞机助推器的核心 然后再加上额外的上面级
But they wanted to reduce costs by using the existing Shuttle launch pads
但他们想通过使用现有的航天飞机发射台来降低成本
so the boosters had to be the same distance apart on the pad
所以助推器必须在发射台上保持相同的距离
as they would be if they were attached to the Space Shuttle's external tank.
这种距离要类似于助推器连接在航天飞机的外部燃料储罐上的那种
And this means that the booster cluster
这意味着这组助推器
looks like they're trying to stay as far away from each other
看起来是要离得越远越好
while working together kind of like they're embarrassed
一旦靠近就会遇到麻烦似的
or maybe they sort of develop some sort of social distancing protocol for rockets.
或者是他们开发出了某种火箭的保持社交距离的协议
Needless to say this concept lost out to the Titan.
当然 这个概念输给了大力神火箭
And then there was the Jupiter 3 laid out by Team Vision Inc in a 2006 paper.
然后是木星3号 由2006年Team Vision股份有限公司的一篇论文中的方案
It was a franken rocket which is served with a massive helping of whiskey tango foxtrot.
它是一个带有大量威士忌探戈狐步舞的科学怪人火箭
This monster heavy lift vehicle would have a core with a pair of Shuttle external tanks
这个怪兽级的重型运载火箭的芯级是一对航天飞机的外部燃料储罐
and each of those would have their own pair of Shuttle boosters attached.
而每一个都会有一对自己的航天飞机助推器
The bottom of the core would have a set of RS-68 engines which would be fueled from the external tanks
芯级的底部将有一套RS-68发动机 它将从外部燃料储罐中获得燃料
which meant that a whole lot dropped off during staging.
这意味着 在分级期间会掉落一大堆东西
After that they would have another couple of core stages
之后 还有几个芯级
and a massive fairing for 160 tons of payload.
和一个可容纳160吨有效载荷的巨大整流罩
In the art they make it look like a pair of Space Shuttles launching the first stage of a Saturn V
在艺术作品中 他们让它看起来像是一对航天飞机在发射土星五号的第一级
which might sound cool to some.
这对某些人来说可能很帅
I'm sorry it's not.
但我不行
For the final few ugly rockets
对于最后几枚丑陋的火箭
let's scale back our dreams and look at some rockets that were never designed to go to space.
让我们缩小梦想的范围 看看一些设计出来并不是要入轨的火箭
First up the Navaho cruise missile an early design for a nuclear cruise missile
首先是核巡航导弹研制初期出现的纳瓦霍巡航导弹
which just looks ridiculously ungainly on the launch pad.
它在发射台上就看起来很难看
It had a rocket booster to get up to speed
它使用一个火箭助推器来加速
and then this would drop away
加速结束之后就会抛弃
and let the supersonic ramjets do the work to bring the payload to the target.
并启动超音速冲压发动机 把有效载荷送到目标位置
If you separated the cruise missile from the booster actually did look kind of cool
如果你把巡航导弹和助推器分开 实际上看起来确实有点帅
but we're talking about the full package here.
但我们在这里谈论的是完整的组合体
Because it was a test program
因为这是一个测试项目
many of the missiles were painted bright colours to make them easy to see
许多导弹被涂成鲜艳的颜色 以便于观察
which doesn't really improve on the random mess of wings engines and intakes that was the Navaho.
而这并没有真正改善纳瓦霍的机翼 发动机和进气道排列所产生的随机混乱感
It never entered service because the Atlas ICBM could do the same thing in less time.
它从未服役 因为宇宙神洲际弹道导弹可以在更短的时间内做同样的事情
Even before this we have the V2 Hermes
甚至在这之前 我们还有V2赫尔墨斯
which put ram jets on top of a V2 rocket with a monster wedge-shaped wing
这是在V2火箭的基础上加装了冲压式发动机以及巨大的楔形翼
that forced them to add even bigger fins on the bottom of the V2 for stability.
这使得他们不得不在V2的底部加装了更大的翼面 以保证稳定性
And this rocket actually caused a bit of an international incident
而这枚火箭其实也引起了一点国际事件
when during one launch it started going the wrong way
在一次发射过程中 火箭一开始就朝错误的方向飞行
and the range safety officer was unable to terminate the flight
而落区安全员无法终止飞行
because one of the rocket designers physically restrained him.
是因为其中一名火箭设计人员对他进行了人身限制
The rocket ended up flying into Mexico and leaving a substantial crater near an airfield.
火箭最终飞入墨西哥 在一个机场附近留下了一个巨大的弹坑
It probably didn't help that
而更糟地是
the engineers had recently been brought over from germany as part of operation paperclip.
这名工程师是最近通过回纹针行动从德国带来的
Finally to show that nothing is sacred here.
最后要说明的是 这里没有什么是神圣的
Goddard's historic achievements in rocketry should not let us forget that
Goddard在火箭领域的历史性成就不应该让我们忘记
not only did his first rocket design look bad
那就是他的第一枚火箭设计不仅看起来很丑
but it was ass backwards with the engines at the top and the fuel tank at the bottom
而且还是上下颠倒的 发动机在上面而燃料储罐在下面
because he thought that this would be more stable.
因为他认为这样会更稳定
Yes the guy that literally invented rocket science also fell for the pendulum rocket fallacy
是的 那个真的发明了火箭科学的家伙也陷入了对火箭审美的摇摆不定当中
but I can forgive him for this misstep on the way to making history.
但我可以原谅他这个失误 因为他创造了历史
Unlike me he didn't have Kerbal Space Program to experiment with first.
不像我 他不能用坎巴拉太空计划先做实验
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]